<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Technology | Geshan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/categories/technology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://geshan.com.np/"/>
  <updated>2018-12-14T21:44:28+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://geshan.com.np/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Geshan Manandhar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[You Can Do It in SQL, Stop Writing Extra Code for That]]></title>
    <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/12/you-can-do-it-in-sql/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-14T19:30:54+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/12/you-can-do-it-in-sql</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>“SQL, Lisp, and Haskell are the only programming languages that I’ve seen where one spends more time thinking than typing.&ldquo; - Philip Greenspun</p>

<p>Even with thinking more than typing SQL (Structured Query Language) we software engineers use it as a way to pull data only.</p>

<blockquote><p>We usually don&rsquo;t leverage SQL&rsquo;s power of data manipulation and do the needed changes in code.</p></blockquote>

<p>This is quite prevalent in software engineers who work in web applications. This post aims to enlighten you about the powers of SQL you might know but generally don&rsquo;t use.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/do-it-in-sql/tea-lights.jpg &lsquo;You can do it in SQL, stop writing extra code for that&rsquo; &lsquo;You can do it in SQL, stop writing extra code for that&rsquo; %}</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>TLDR;</h2>

<blockquote><p>Use SQL to do math like sum, average etc. Utilize it for grouping one to many relational values like getting categories of product. Leverage SQL for string manipulation like using CONCAT_WS for concating first name and last name. Exploit SQL to sort by a custom priority formula. Examples below&hellip;</p></blockquote>

<h2>The Example</h2>

<p>It will be easier to explain the superpowers of SQL putting it in action on an example. Below is a basic schema with 2 tables in MYSQL for a refunds microservice:</p>

<p>{% img center /images/do-it-in-sql/refund-schema.png &lsquo;You can do it in SQL- refund schema&rsquo; &lsquo;You can do it in SQL - refund schema example&rsquo; %}</p>

<p>There are 2 refunds and 7 related payments as example <a href="http://sqlfiddle.com/#!9/b242d/5">data</a>.</p>

<h3>Some assumptions</h3>

<p>For the refunds microservice example schema and applications following assumptions are made:</p>

<ol>
<li>Refunds microservice and data structure store the fk_item (the id of the ordered/delivered item), but it is not a hard foreign key.</li>
<li>Item can be refunded in either cash or credit for the amount paid for the same.</li>
<li>Items can be refunded many times as long as remaining balance can cover requested refund amount for each cash and credit. For example, item was paid 50 in cash and 50 in credit. 2 refunds of 20 cash and 20 credit can be done. So after these transactions balance will be 10 cash and 10 credit for that item (50-20-20).</li>
<li>Each refund can have multiple items payment. Each payment can be of type either cash or credit.</li>
<li>All amounts are stored in cents so they are integers.</li>
</ol>


<p>Now let&rsquo;s use some SQL powers. You can find the example with related queries running on <a href="http://sqlfiddle.com/#!9/b242d/5">SQL Fiddle</a>.</p>

<h3>Do the math in SQL</h3>

<p>As software engineers, let&rsquo;s say if we need to find the total cash and credit amount refunded for an item what would we do? We would run something like:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT fk_item, fk_refund, amount, is_cash 
FROM payment WHERE fk_item=2001;
</code></pre>

<p>With current data, it will give 3 rows like below:</p>

<p>{% img center /images/do-it-in-sql/01result-without-group.png &lsquo;Result without grouping and aggregate function sum&rsquo; &lsquo;Result without grouping and aggregate function sum&rsquo; %}</p>

<p>With these 3 rows, we would loop over them. If it is cash accumulate it to cashBalance variable, if not sum it up to creditBalace variable. Rather than that it would be a lot easier (probably faster) to do in SQL like:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT fk_item, SUM(amount) AS total_paid, 
IF(is_cash = 1, 'cash', 'credit') as type
FROM payment 
WHERE fk_item = 2001 
GROUP BY fk_item, is_cash;
</code></pre>

<p>Resulting in:</p>

<p>{% img center /images/do-it-in-sql/02result-with-grouping.png &lsquo;Result with grouping and aggregate function sum&rsquo; &lsquo;Result with grouping and aggregate function sum&rsquo; %}</p>

<p>The result is easy now if you need the total refund for the item just change the GROUP BY to be on fk_item and it&rsquo;s done. For 2 and 3 records it won&rsquo;t feel significant. If there were say 20 refunds for that item, the first solution with a loop is writing more code with no gain.  Like sum, other SQL functions can be used too. Simple math operations like <a href="https://www.w3schools.com/sql/func_mysql_sum.asp">sum</a>, multiply, <a href="https://www.w3schools.com/sql/func_mysql_avg.asp">average</a> etc can be easy with SQL. This means no more loops.</p>

<h3>Use GROUP_CONCAT to fetch related 1:m relation values</h3>

<p><a href="http://www.mysqltutorial.org/mysql-group_concat/">Group concat</a> is a powerful operation in SQL databases. It is very useful when you need to get data from one to many relationship. For instance, you want to get all tags for a blog post or you want to get all categories of a product. Concerning this refunds example, one item can be refunded multiple times. So we will get all the refunds associated with the item id. To get this we will run only 1 query and get it without any loops in the code like below:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT fk_item, 
GROUP_CONCAT(DISTINCT fk_refund) refund_ids FROM payment
WHERE fk_item = 2001;
</code></pre>

<p>This results in:</p>

<p>{% img center /images/do-it-in-sql/03result-group-concat.png &lsquo;Result with group_concat&rsquo; &lsquo;Result with group_concat&rsquo; %}</p>

<p>Now we know that item 2001 has been refunded twice for 2 refunds. It will be easy to explode the refund Ids with <code>,</code> and proceed with any related operation.</p>

<h3>String manipulation</h3>

<p>Many <a href="https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/8.0/en/string-functions.html">string manipulation</a> tasks like substring, concatenation, change case, and string compare can be done in SQL. With this example, I am going to show the usage of <code>CONCAT_WS</code>. It is concat with a separator. It can also be used to select for instance first_name and last_name with space in between.</p>

<blockquote><p>In case of having an optional middle name <code>COALESCE</code> can be used with <code>CONCAT_WS</code>. That is something for you to explore :).</p></blockquote>

<p>In this example, I will select refund_nr with it&rsquo;s related reason:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT CONCAT_WS("-", refund_nr, reason) AS refund_nr_with_reason
FROM refund;
</code></pre>

<p>Resulting in:</p>

<p>{% img center /images/do-it-in-sql/04result-concat-ws.png &lsquo;Result with concat_ws&rsquo; &lsquo;Result with concat_ws&rsquo; %}</p>

<p>If this needs to be shown on the credit note document, for example, no extra code is needed to join the values again. SQL makes it one step easier again.</p>

<h3>Sorting with a custom formula</h3>

<p>All software engineers know you can sort based on a column. But if you are given a custom priority formula to sort, what would you do? Probably again resort back to code and loop to sort. So lets set the priority formula rules for above example:</p>

<ol>
<li>Premium customer refunds get the highest priority (we hack it with a priority of 9999999999)</li>
<li>Other than premium customers cash refunds get a priority of amount * 25 for credit it is amount * 20.</li>
</ol>


<p>As per above rules it is decided that premium customers and priority above 50000 (in cents) will be processed first. Then other refunds will be processes. Let&rsquo;s get the priority refunds as below:</p>

<pre><code>SELECT r.refund_nr, r.reason, p.fk_item, p.amount, p.is_cash, 
IF(p.premium_customer = 1, 9999999999, p.amount * (IF(is_cash = 1, 25, 20))) AS priority FROM 
refund AS r INNER JOIN payment AS p ON r.id = p.fk_refund
HAVING priority &gt; 50000
ORDER BY priority DESC
</code></pre>

<p>The results are below:</p>

<p>{% img center /images/do-it-in-sql/05result-priority-formula.png &lsquo;Result with sorting based on custom formula&rsquo; &lsquo;Result with sorting based on custom formula&rsquo; %}</p>

<p>With proper use of IF in SQL sorting by a custom priority formula is a lot easier than trying to do it with loops in code. Notice that even smaller amounts like 7.5 (750 cents) and 9.0 (900 cents) came to highest priority as these refund payment amounts were associated with premium customers.</p>

<blockquote><p>Use the superpowers of SQL to make your life easier as a software engineer.</p></blockquote>

<p>You can play with the example and run your own queries on <a href="http://sqlfiddle.com/#!9/b242d/5">SQL fiddle</a>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>There are other tricks of SQL that can help you as a software engineer. Like <code>UPDATE</code> with <code>INSERT</code> using <code>ON DUPLICATE KEY UPDATE</code>. Whenever you have an itch of doing some manipulation for data pulled in from database in code with loops, think again. The main takeaway from this story is:</p>

<blockquote><p>Exploit the power of SQL to write less code because &ldquo;the best code is the code that was never written&rdquo;. If it is not written there is no need to maintain it.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Tech Medium Publications Software Engineers Should Strive to Write For]]></title>
    <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/12/5-tech-medium-publications-software-engineers-should-strive-to-write-for/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-05T19:16:06+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/12/5-tech-medium-publications-software-engineers-should-strive-to-write-for</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Starting a tech blog has changed in the last few years. 10 years back starting a blog without your website, you had 2 options Blogger or Wordpress. Both gave you a free sub-domain. Things did not change much for quite some time, but in 2012 medium came with a storm. It gained a lot of traction with its simplistic interface in 2014-2015. With the publication feature, Medium makes it very easy for a group of writers to collaborate.  These days I would suggest most people start their blog on it.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/5-tech-medium-publications/library.jpg &lsquo;5 tech medium publication software engineers should strive to write for&rsquo; &lsquo;5 tech medium publication software engineers should strive to write for&rsquo; %}</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Writing is tough, learning is essential</h2>

<p>Writing is never easy for most people. If you don&rsquo;t try it you never know if it is something you like or not.</p>

<blockquote><p>“A writer is someone for whom writing is more difficult than it is for other people.” ― Thomas Mann</p></blockquote>

<p>Writing is another form of expressing yourself. As people working in the tech domain, we need this skill of expressing ourselves well. Similarly, reading and learning about new things is also very important in our field. Learning is essential to survive in tech and move forward. Open source software there are a lot of consumers compared to producers. Likewise, there are a lot of readers for tech content but relatively much fewer writers.</p>

<h2>Tech Medium publications accepting writers</h2>

<p>Below are the tech publications on Medium I would suggest all software engineers to follow to sharpen their skills:</p>

<h3><a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/">FreeCodeCamp</a> - 511K followers</h3>

<p>FreeCodeCamp is the place to go for learning how to code for free. It has a very popular and frequently updated publication on Medium. The content published on FreeCodeCamp blog is excellent. There are 17 editors and more than a 1K+ writers on this publication. You will need to read this elaborate blog <a href="http://bit.ly/how-to-submit">post</a> to know how to submit your story there. Writing for them is not easy, they also do light editing of your stories. Even if your story gets accepted it could have a wait time of 1-2 weeks to be published (my first story for them is still in the pipeline).  All in all you must try to get your stories published there because of the sheer number of subscribers. It is #2 on <a href="https://toppub.xyz/">toppub.xyz</a>.</p>

<h3><a href="https://hackernoon.com/">HackerNoon</a> - 403kK followers</h3>

<p>HackerNoon is also another extremely popular publication. It is on Medium right now but it may not be there for long. They are going public with <a href="https://www.startengine.com/hackernoon">crowd sourcing</a>. From the content point of view, there is a sizable amount of content for software engineers. It also has lots of stories on cryptocurrencies. With 7 editors and 7K+ writers (includes me), this is a huge publication too. To write for them you need to send your draft to <a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#x6c;&#116;&#x6f;&#58;&#83;&#116;&#111;&#x72;&#x69;&#x65;&#115;&#x40;&#x41;&#x4d;&#x69;&#80;&#117;&#98;&#108;&#105;&#99;&#x61;&#x74;&#105;&#x6f;&#110;&#115;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;&#x2e;">&#83;&#116;&#x6f;&#114;&#105;&#x65;&#x73;&#x40;&#65;&#77;&#x69;&#x50;&#x75;&#98;&#x6c;&#x69;&#x63;&#x61;&#x74;&#x69;&#x6f;&#110;&#x73;&#46;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;&#x2e;</a> The wait time for each story is 1 week or more (I have already published 5 stories). It also has a writer&rsquo;s group on Facebook. You can include yourself as a &ldquo;Contributing Writer&rdquo; on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/hackernoon/">LinkedIn</a> too.</p>

<h3><a href="https://codeburst.io">CodeBurst.io</a> - 62K followers</h3>

<p>CodeBurst is a popular medium publication with contents focused on web development. With a motto of &ldquo;Bursts of code to power through your day&rdquo;. I  see most stories geared towards Javascript. They have a page encouraging &ldquo;<a href="https://codeburst.io/how-to-write-for-codeburst-io-63fec4bf111c">Write For Us</a>&rdquo;. They mention having over 2 million page views per month. With 2 Editors and more than 900 writers, this is not a small Medium publication. I am not sure of the editorial process and wait times as I have not tried to publish any of my stories here. It could be a good starting point for new writers.</p>

<h3><a href="https://itnext.io">ITNEXT.io</a> -  9.6K followers</h3>

<p>ITNEXT seems to cover a wider array of topics from DevOps to Javascript. It calls itself  &ldquo;a platform for IT developers &amp; software engineers to share knowledge, connect, collaborate, learn and experience next-gen technologies&rdquo;. It has a short and to the point &ldquo;Write for ITNEXT&rdquo; <a href="https://itnext.io/write-for-itnext-4dea1fd3adf">page</a> with enough details on how to submit a story to them. With 7 editors and 840+ writers, it is undoubtedly a growing publication I reckon.  I can&rsquo;t comment on the waiting time for a story to be published on this one too.</p>

<h3><a href="https://blog.bitsrc.io">Bits and Pieces</a> - 8.5K followers</h3>

<p>Bits and Pieces look like a pretty active tech medium publication. It has content covering topics like NodeJs, PHP and mobile development. With a motto of &ldquo;Coding In The Age Of Code Components&rdquo;. It somewhat lives up to it. It has detailed &ldquo;Write a post&rdquo; <a href="https://blog.bitsrc.io/how-to-write-a-post-for-bits-and-pieces-13de0133151b">page</a> which includes lots of examples. With 5 editors and more than 65 writers, it is an expanding publication. I think the barrier to entry should not be that high. The waiting time for a story to be published should be less as well.</p>

<h2>Popular Niche Ones</h2>

<p>I would like to mention some popular niche publications. First one is <a href="https://medium.com/dailyjs">DailyJs</a> with 89K followers have a &ldquo;Submit Your Story&rdquo; <a href="https://medium.com/dailyjs/how-to-submit-your-story-to-dailyjs-30f02b2d5287">page</a>. <a href="https://uxdesign.cc/">UX Collective</a> with 228K follower is also <a href="https://uxdesign.cc/submit-your-article-to-uxdesign-cc-abea95d3a1ba">calling for stories</a>. Last but not least, <a href="https://uxplanet.org/">UX Planet</a> having 173K followers also wants you to write for <a href="https://uxplanet.org/how-to-publish-your-content-on-ux-planet-fd9dc99756db">them</a>.</p>

<h2>Honorable Mention</h2>

<p>Though <a href="https://dev.to/">dev.to</a> is not a Medium publication but it surely deserves a place here.</p>

<blockquote><p>Currently the 11,357th website in the world, it has no editorial process.</p></blockquote>

<p>This makes it one of the most accessible website to write for that without doubts has a big audience. I got <a href="https://dev.to/geshan">2250+ followers</a> on Dev.to in less than 2 months having just 20 posts.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t accentuate your skills and knowledge people are not going to know about them automatically. Start a blog and write posts for such popular platforms. It will give you that needed exposure. Start blogging!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[4 Ways Docker Changed the Way Software Engineers Work in Past Half Decade]]></title>
    <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/12/4-ways-docker-changed-the-way-software-engineers-work-in-past-half-decade/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-01T09:14:51+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/12/4-ways-docker-changed-the-way-software-engineers-work-in-past-half-decade</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>10 years back it was Git that transformed the way software engineers worked. Half a decade back it was <a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a> that brought the container to the masses. Before Docker, container was like a sacred secret in companies like Google and Heroku. Docker is a software and a company too. It tried to build a broader ecosystem but <a href="https://kubernetes.io/">Kubernetes</a> stole the thunder along the way keeping <a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/swarm/">swarm</a> at bay. This post is not about how some Docker tools are not popular. It is about how Docker has changed the way we work in the past 5 years.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/4-ways-docker/docker-whale.jpg &lsquo;4 ways Docker changed the way software engineers work in past half decade&rsquo; &lsquo;4 ways Docker changed the way software engineers work in past half decade&rsquo; %}</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>TLDR;</h2>

<blockquote><p>With Docker, you ship the whole stack not only your code. Allocate minimum required resources to containers then scale them horizontally. With containers security generally already comes baked In. With Docker and Kubernetes you can get zero downtime and faster deployments leading to business profit.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Changed the ways</h2>

<p>If you want to go to the technical details of what is a container and why to use docker Google it :).</p>

<blockquote><p>Docker has also partially deprecated many of the configuration management tools.</p></blockquote>

<p>This post is about how Docker has changed the way we work after its release in March 2013. Below are some reasons that helped advance our way of working:</p>

<h3>Ship the whole stack, not just code</h3>

<p>With containers and Docker in specific, you always ship the whole stack in each version. The whole image gets rebuilt every time. It includes the precise OS+version, specific version of the language. It also has the dependencies like the framework and other libraries (versions depend on how you handle it). It also includes the code you have written and this results in a significant advantage. The advantage is, if it built correctly on your machine, it will potentially build on the server too. As soon as it runs it is the exact same environment on dev, staging, testing and even on production.</p>

<blockquote><p>It happens because you didn&rsquo;t shop only the code, you shipped your code + vendor code + specific language version + precise OS version too.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Allocate only needed resources to the application and scale horizontally</h3>

<p>With each Docker container, you can be specific about how much resources you want to allocate to that particular container. Using software like Kubernetes it becomes so much easier to scale your application. Under high load, the no. of containers can expand and with less load, it can shrink too. So with this mechanism, each container (or pod for Kubernetes) can be allocated the minimum resources and scaled horizontally as per need.</p>

<blockquote><p>For example, a simple Node JS app container/pod can run with like 128 MB memory and 0.25 CPU. As and when load increases run 5 pods in place of 2.</p></blockquote>

<p>This requires the application to be built with horizontal scalability in mind. That basically means storing no data on the file system. Treating containers like cattle, not pet helps scale horizontally. It also makes high availability of application an achievable task.</p>

<h3>Security is baked in</h3>

<p>Using a container, not virtual machine the attack surface is already decreased. Following container security best practices you can already improve your security measures. Of course, if you have holes in the application like SQL injection that is a different story. Still, with smaller and security-focused images like Alpine, it will be easier to get the basics right.</p>

<blockquote><p>Security is always about keeping the attack surface small. With containers and Docker closing more doors become easier.</p></blockquote>

<p>The container should have access to only what it needs. As the file system is temporary for containers it can be a security boon as well as a security auditing issue.</p>

<h3>Deploy faster with zero downtime</h3>

<p>Deploying Docker containers is always about shipping the whole stack. So the chances of one file not syncing or one server not getting the latest changes are not there. As a successful build of the image is always required to deploy it any problems will be found in the build process.</p>

<blockquote><p>With software like Kubernetes and Helm, orchestrating and deploying containers become straightforward. With High Availability (HA) in place using proper load balancing, deployments can be zero downtime.</p></blockquote>

<p>Easier and faster deployment equates to the ability to deploy smaller changes. Smaller changes done well can lead to a better response to market needs quickly. To sum up, use the right tools to deploy your containers in a way to use it for business advantage.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The past 5 years have seen rapid adoption of Docker. With tools like Kubernetes deploying and scaling applications has been much effortless than some years ago.</p>

<blockquote><p>Don&rsquo;t worship your virtual machines, use the resources it provides efficiently. Get on the Docker and containers train and reap its benefits.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Signs That Reveal Your Software Development Process Is Agile Only on Paper and Solutions for Them]]></title>
    <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/11/5-signs-that-reveal-your-software-development-process-is-agile-only-on-paper-and-solutions-for-them/"/>
    <updated>2018-11-20T20:00:22+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/11/5-signs-that-reveal-your-software-development-process-is-agile-only-on-paper-and-solutions-for-them</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Agility comes with practice not putting big words on paper. Using Jira does not make your software development process agile. Saying we do &ldquo;scrum&rdquo; is not being agile. Being agile is having an agile mindset and putting it into practice everyday. It is about thinking about the value you deliver to the customer and how to do it better.  This post will also unveil these 5 signs and how to solve these issues. The signs and solutions will concern multiple roles like Product Manager, Software engineer etc.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/5-signs-agile-on-paper/board.jpg &lsquo;5 signs that reveal your company is agile only on paper and solutions for them&rsquo; &lsquo;5 signs that reveal your company is agile only on paper and solutions for them&rsquo; %}</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>TLDR;</h2>

<blockquote><p>If you are writing documents > 5 pages you can improve. There should be a clear definition of Ready for development and Done. Story/Issue should be based on value delivered to the customer not only the technical aspect. Releasing a new version of software once a month and saying we are agile should be a crime. Not caring about the team is not doing agile right.</p></blockquote>

<p>Below are the signs that explain why the paper boat agility will not work and how to fix them:</p>

<h2>Documents that are longer than 5 pages</h2>

<p>There will be big features (epics) and they have to be explained. This does not give you a license to write 50 pager documents. If a document is longer than 5 pages many team members will not read it, accept this fact.</p>

<blockquote><p>One beautiful Monday morning you get a memo of 30 pages text about the new feature business wants us to develop. Will you read it thoroughly? The answer is No.</p></blockquote>

<p>You might skim through it to sustain in the meeting and that&rsquo;s about it. Documents become obsolete fast. When requirements change no one bothers to update documentation.</p>

<h3>Solution</h3>

<p> Write documents that are less than or equal to 5 pages. Make it concise and precise. Start creating visual aids for the process to explain it. Create mock-ups, use tools like <a href="https://balsamiq.com/">Balsamiq</a>. Express the requirements in a way that is understood by everyone with less or no reading involved. Then as per need create a UI design and discuss. After that implement it in code.</p>

<h2>Unclear definition of Ready for development and Done</h2>

<p>Definition of ready for development and Done are crucial for team success. Not having these or having unclear ones will hamper the team performance.</p>

<blockquote><p>A software engineer should be clear about when the story is ready to be picked up for development. Same goes for Done.</p></blockquote>

<p>Is it ready for development when the story is created but the description does not exist? Is it done as soon as I deploy it to production and move my task to &ldquo;Done&rdquo; column? If there are confusions like these it is a bad smell that needs to be addressed.</p>

<h3>Solution</h3>

<p>Have a clear point by point &ldquo;Definition of Ready&rdquo; and &ldquo;Definition of Done&rdquo;. This will help to measure and improve team performance. It will also assist in everyone involved to understand the meaning of these things the same way.</p>

<h2>Stories based on the technical aspect not value to a customer</h2>

<p>Agile software development is always about delivering value to the customer. The value in the form of working software not a pile of documents. If there a story like &ldquo;As a customer service manager I need to know who created a refund so that I can track and audit refunds in future&rdquo;. This task might entail adding a &ldquo;created_by&rdquo; field in the refunds table for instance. But this should not result in having a &ldquo;story&rdquo; that says &ldquo;Add created_by field in the refunds table&rdquo;. Of course, it can be a task/subtask as part of the main story. The main story delivers value but this database task is something that aids the process.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/5-signs-agile-on-paper/story.jpg &lsquo;5 signs that reveal your company is agile only on paper and solutions for them&rsquo; &lsquo;5 signs that reveal your company is agile only on paper and solutions for them&rsquo; %}</p>

<h3>Solution</h3>

<p>Have clear definitions and boundaries of Epic, Story, and task.  Each story should deliver some value to the customer (as above picture).  If you are following Scrum you will have story points too for things like team velocity. Technical tasks are required. Still, only the right sum of technical tasks deliver value to the customer.</p>

<blockquote><p>The main thing here is &ldquo;always focus on the value being delivered to the customer&rdquo;.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Releasing a new version of software once a month</h2>

<p>The first thing to consider here is:</p>

<blockquote><p>Deployment is a technical task and releasing a new software version is a business activity.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/10/deployment-is-not-release/">Deployment is not release</a>. If you are not able to make that distinction there is something that needs to be fixed. On top of it, if you hardly release one new version each month, you are doing agile wrong.  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Release_early,_release_often">Release early release often</a> is an excellent philosophy to get feedback early. With early feedback, you can make a new set of changes in the next release to make the software better. This might not apply for mobile applications with long vendor approval process. For web applications deploying and releasing multiple times a day should be a norm.</p>

<h3>Solution</h3>

<p>Build a culture and technical process to be able to deploy and/or release to production multiple times a day.</p>

<blockquote><p>Enforce good code quality and excellent software engineering practices. Follow tried and tested best practices like code reviews, automated testing, CI/CD, <a href="https://geshan.com.np/blog/2015/08/importance-of-logging-in-your-applications/">logging</a>, monitoring, and <a href="https://geshan.com.np/blog/2015/08/the-best-automated-deployment-tool-the-one-that-fits-your-needs/">automated deployment</a>.</p></blockquote>

<p>Call it DevOps, SRE or Platforms engineering whatever you want but do it and deploy without fear whenever you want.</p>

<h2>Not being careful about team motivation</h2>

<p>Software development is a team sport. If one player is hurt the team covers for that player. If one team member lacks some skills team covers and helps teach that skill to the team member. Self organizing team that reflects on how to make the process better is at the heart of agile.</p>

<blockquote><p>Team motivation and happy team members are essential to high productivity.</p></blockquote>

<p>If you are being treated like story executors with no voice and no room for improvement, it is a big bad sign.</p>

<h3>Solution</h3>

<p>Build a culture of continuous improvement. Reflect on things that have been done and how the process can be enhanced. For instance, if doing 60% new features and 40% bugs did not work well, find a better ratio. Do team activities and things that uplift the team spirit.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Being agile on paper and being agile in practice are two different things. Don&rsquo;t let your agile software process be like waterfall with the so-labeled agile skin. Be agile and fix these signs to have high team output with fantastic performance.</p>

<blockquote><p>Agile should be implemented to solve people and communication problems which results in stabilizing the technical issues.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving From a and B to 150 Microservices, the Journey, and Learnings [Slides]]]></title>
    <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/10/moving-from-a-and-b-to-~150-microservices/"/>
    <updated>2018-10-27T08:08:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://geshan.com.np/blog/2018/10/moving-from-a-and-b-to-~150-microservices</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I gave a talk at #devopsdaysNewy on 24-Oct-2018. It was a great conference with lots of amazing people.
I want to thank the organizers for putting together such an amazing event. I want to extend the thanks to the sponsors who made it possible :). It was very good couple of days to meet new people and form a network. I think my talk on microservices went pretty good too. It was my second devops days and I enjoyed it.</p>

<p>{% img center /images/a-b-to-150-ms/150-ms-geshan.jpg &lsquo;Moving from A and B to 150 microservices, the journey, and learnings&rsquo; &lsquo;Moving from A and B to 150 microservices, the journey, and learnings&rsquo; %}</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The abstract</h2>

<p>Are you frustrated working with large, legacy and potentially lethal code bases? We were frustrated too,but in 4-5 years of time, we replaced A (front-end) and B (back-office) system with ~150 microservices. From the days of no tests and clumsy deployment process, we moved to each service with unit tests, CI and deploying with a bot. With the business buying in the process, we enabled the business to reach new heights. This talk reveals that journey and the things we learned along the way.</p>

<h2>The slides</h2>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="05a92573b3fc4221b6a17478ae0db2b2" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p>Slides on <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/geshan/moving-from-a-and-b-to-150-microservices-the-journey-and-learnings">slide share</a></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I gave the same talk at Node Sydney <a href="https://www.meetup.com/node-sydney/events/cvdqzpyxmbjb/">September meetup</a> that went pretty well too. Hope to be able to give more talks in future and meet more interesting people.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
