<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Git | Geshan's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/categories/git/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://geshan.com.np/"/>
  <updated>2018-09-29T17:33:06+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://geshan.com.np/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Geshan Manandhar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Developers Nepal Meetup #16 a Round Up and My Talk on Simpilfied Gitflow With Slides]]></title>
    <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2016/06/php-developers-nepal-meetup-number-16-a-round-up-and-my-simpilfied-gitflow-talk/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-25T21:50:35+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://geshan.com.np/blog/2016/06/php-developers-nepal-meetup-number-16-a-round-up-and-my-simpilfied-gitflow-talk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had given a talk in the PHP Developers Nepal meetup #14 in Aug 2014 about <a href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2014/08/basic-overview-of-message-queues-rabbit/">Rabbit Mq and Symfony</a>.
This time the <a href="http://developers-nepal.github.io/php/meetups/25-Jun-2016/">meetup</a> took place at
Prime College today. There were 2 regular talks for this meetup and one 5 minute lightening
talk about the community. For this 16th installment, we did an open discussion for the first time.
The topic of open discussion was &ldquo;Does automated deployment and DevOps add value to the organization?&rdquo;.
It was the highlight of the event.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/php-dev-meetup-16/php-dev-meetup-16.jpg" title="&lsquo;PHP Dev Meetup 16 Open Panel discussion on DevOps&rsquo; &lsquo;PHP Dev Meetup 16 Open Panel discussion on DevOps&rsquo;" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>How did it all unfold</h2>

<p>The first talk was given by Amrit GC on &ldquo;Ansible for PHP Developers&rdquo;, then I presented my talk on &ldquo;Simplified Gitflow&rdquo;.
After those two regular talks we had a lightening talk presented by Manish Jung Thapa (MJT) on PHP Developers Nepal Community.
Last part of the program was an open discussion on &ldquo;Does automated deployment and DevOps add value to the organization?&rdquo; which
got a lot of questions from the audience. It was great to moderate the open discussion. Overall, it was an amazing meetup. I guess
there were around 100 participants which makes it one of the biggest PHP Developers meetup in terms of audience size.</p>

<h2>My Talk on Simplified Gitflow</h2>

<p>This is not the first time I presented this talk :). I had already given this talk at <a href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2015/09/how-to-use-simplified-gitflow-branching-model-video/">YIPL in Mar 2015</a>.
This time I changed the slides and made it more general. I hope it was helpful to the audience.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/php-dev-meetup-16/simplified-gitflow-talk.jpg" title="&lsquo;PHP Dev Meetup 16 My talk on simplified gitflow&rsquo; &lsquo;PHP Dev Meetup 16 My talk on simplified gitflow&rsquo;" ></p>

<h2>Slides of Simplified Gitflow</h2>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="acdf3ecb8fd84007b33113d906e5dd3c" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<h2>Video of my talk on Simplified Gitflow</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jznORrhoV-M?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>More vidoes of the full event in this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLhTqkNYfkucxGk2OssIseNLMF9jPXYoHC">playlist</a>.</p>

<h2>Hope to see more meetups</h2>

<blockquote><p>Hope there will be a Developers Nepal meetup which is language agnostic soon. Kudos.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3 Simple Rules for Less or No Git Conflicts]]></title>
    <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2016/04/3-simple-rules-for-less-or-no-git-conflicts/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-28T16:14:43+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://geshan.com.np/blog/2016/04/3-simple-rules-for-less-or-no-git-conflicts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Do you write at least 10 lines of code a day in any programming language? Do you work alone or in a team?
If your answer is yes to both questions, you need to learn <code>git</code> even if you work alone in a project.
<a href="https://git-scm.com/">Git</a> is the most popular versions control system and it has become a must have
software engineer skill.</p>

<p>I have seen teams fall into this trap of git conflicts when they start using git and some type of
<a href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2014/12/do-you-git-your-code-follow-this-simplified-gitflow-model/">gitflow</a>.
Merging branches to the main branch becomes a pain when there are git conflicts.
In this post I am going to reveal 3 simple rules to avoid git conflicts.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/3-rules-git-conflict/git-conflict.png" title="&lsquo;3 simple rules for less or no git conflicts&rsquo; &lsquo;3 simple rules for less or no git conflicts&rsquo;" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Assumption</h2>

<p>You have some working knowledge of git. You follow a git branching model like gitflow or simplified gitflow.</p>

<h2>Rule 1: Keep your changes small</h2>

<p>This is the golden rule to avoid git conflicts in teams. Conflicts occurs when 2 team members make changes
around the same line of code. Like John changes like 5-10 in readme.md. Jack changes like 7-15 in the same
readme.md file on a different branch. Have a rule of thumb that each pull request can have at most 20 files
changed with 200 line addition. If changes are less there is less chances of having things overlapped. As a
side effect, it will make deploying and testing changes easy too.</p>

<h2>Rule 2: Rebase with your main branch (generally master) when it changes</h2>

<p>When your main branch changes, rebase the branch you are working on with it. Usually <code>master</code> is the
main branch so it will be best if you rebase with master at least once a day. This saves you from bringing
in lots of changes done by other team member late. Its the same concept as above, get small changes step by
step many times than getting it all at once. At the end of the day always do the following, given
you are on your working branch</p>

<pre><code>git checkout master
git fetch
git pull --rebase origin master
git checkout -
git rebase master
</code></pre>

<p>You get the latest master. Then you go back to your previous branch and rebase your branch with latest master.</p>

<h2>Rule 3: Review pull requests faster and merge them to main branch</h2>

<p>As I have stated earlier &ldquo;An open pull request (PR) is a liability in at least 2 ways. 1 it’s a feature/fix not
shipped to customers. 2 it will invite code conflicts soon.&rdquo; Have a rule, pull requests need action by 3 days of
opening them. You can review code, if code is ok deploy and merge or review code, fix issues then deploy and merge.
This will help the team ship things faster as well as not have pull requests open unattended for weeks.</p>

<h3>Useful Tip</h3>

<p>You followed the above rules, still landed in a git conflict situation? Use <code>git cherry-pick</code>. If you have more
than one commit in your working branch first <a href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2014/07/4-git-tips-beyond-basics/">squash</a>
it to one commit. Then create a new branch out of master/your main branch and do <code>git cherry-pick &lt;sha-of-your-squashed-commit&gt;</code>.<br/>
Given you have only 1 commit on your working branch <code>feature11</code> and you are on <code>feature11</code> right now, do the following:</p>

<pre><code>git checkout master; git fetch &amp;&amp; git pull --rebase origin master
git checkout -b feature-11-new
git cherry-pick 249bd9b150fdb1e6fc9e58af9823f70cc52579a3
</code></pre>

<p>In the above example <code>249bd9b150fdb1e6fc9e58af9823f70cc52579a3</code> is used for demo only. You can know your SHA hash with <code>git log -1</code>
being on branch <code>feature11</code></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>There is no silver bullet to avoid git conflicts all the time. You will face it now and then.
If you run into git conflicts everyday the process and system needs to change.
Be logical, if you have a PR with 50 files changed and 700 new lines you will face conflicts.</p>

<blockquote><p>I hope you face less git conflicts or even completely avoid them.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Use Simplified Gitflow Branching Model [Video]]]></title>
    <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2015/09/how-to-use-simplified-gitflow-branching-model-video/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-25T23:16:23+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://geshan.com.np/blog/2015/09/how-to-use-simplified-gitflow-branching-model-video</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just knowing git and all team members pushing code to the main branch (master) is not a good practice.
To leverage the most out of git, it is a good idea to do feature branching and follow a branching model.
GitFlow is one of the options for doing a feature branching model but it is not so straight forward,
In this blog post with a video and presentation I would elaborate on how a team can use <code>simplified gitflow</code>
and get the most out of using git.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/simplified-gitflow/simple-git-flow.jpg" title="&lsquo;Simplified git-flow&rsquo; &lsquo;Simplified git-flow&rsquo;" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Slides</h2>

<center><iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/42503092" width="510" height="420" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe></center>


<p>You can also view the <a href="http://bit.ly/1KzaNbj">interactive slides</a>.</p>

<h2>Video</h2>

<center><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/nwM2U-38JP8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></center>


<p>I talk about git flow for the first 15-16 minutes then I start answering questions on git and gitflow. Then
I explain about other things in git which can be helpful. I did this presentation at <a href="http://yipl.com.np">YIPL</a>
on 11-Mar-2015. I know its a late post its like a part 2 of <a href="http://bit.ly/s-git-flow">Do you git your code? Follow this simplified gitflow branching model to improve productivity</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>Hope you learn something new about git and simplified gitflow from this video.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Software Engineering Practices in Nepal Infographics Part 2 Includes Git, VCS Hosting, Code Review Culture Etc]]></title>
    <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2015/05/software-engineering-practices-in-nepal-infographics-part-2-includes-git/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-22T12:40:58+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://geshan.com.np/blog/2015/05/software-engineering-practices-in-nepal-infographics-part-2-includes-git</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I hope life is slowly going back to normal in Nepal though the news of aftershocks is not encouraging. My prayers are with the
people of Nepal and I hope they get the positive energy to resume with their normal work.</p>

<p>Below is the Part 2 of the Software Engineering Practices in Nepal Infographics. This time the graphical information covers
popularity of Versioin Control System (VCS), VCS hosting, Operating System (OS), Coding Standard, Code Reviews and other
interesting facts from the survey.</p>

<p>Again special thanks to <a href="http://bit.ly/ashish-singh-blog">Ashish Singh</a> for helping
me clean up and compile the data in a better way. And this time even <a href="http://bit.ly/ansu-blog">Ansubha Manandhar</a> rolled up
her sleeves and helped us group and compile the data into percentages, thank you for that.</p>

<p><strong>Data for this infographics is taken from this <a href="http://bit.ly/nep-dev-survey">survey</a>, I kindly request you to fill it.</strong></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/sw-eng-np-infographics-part02/Software_Engineering_Nepal_Mid_2015_Part02.png" title="&lsquo;Software Engineering Practices in Nepal Infographics Part 2&rsquo; &lsquo;Software Engineering Practices in Nepal Infographics Part 2&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>You can view this infographics in <a href="http://bit.ly/1R8EfHQ">interactive</a> mode too.</p>

<p><strong>If you enjoyed viewing the infographics, I again request to fill up the <a href="http://bit.ly/nep-dev-survey">survey</a> if you have not filled it up yet.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>Thanks to everyone filling up the survey even in such conditions in Nepal.
I hope to get some more responses so that the next infographics in this series will have more data.
I will make the survey open till 2015 Q3 and post the final results in Oct 2015. #prayForNepal #stayStrongNepal #rebuildNepal</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do You Git Your Code? Follow This Simplified Gitflow Branching Model to Improve Productivity]]></title>
    <link href="http://geshan.com.np/blog/2014/12/do-you-git-your-code-follow-this-simplified-gitflow-model/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-13T14:52:40+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://geshan.com.np/blog/2014/12/do-you-git-your-code-follow-this-simplified-gitflow-model</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Git or a similar VCS is the backbone for code collaboration in a multi-developers environment. When you follow
a proper branch naming convention, git branching and merging can also be tied to an issue flow for better
project management.</p>

<p>Source code Version Control System (VCS) and automated testing open doors to other great software quality and
delivery practices like continuous integration and automated deployment etc. Amongst various version control
system software <a href="http://git-scm.com">git</a> is a distributed system that is very popular and easy to use once
you get used to it.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/simplified-gitflow/simple-git-flow.jpg" title="&lsquo;Simplified git-flow&rsquo; &lsquo;Simplified git-flow&rsquo;" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The full <a href="hhttp://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model/">gitflow</a> has 3 perpetual branches develop,
release and master. Tickets/Issues can be grouped to release from develop. This in turn creates difficulty when
tracing the ticket that caused any problem when it occurs.</p>

<p>Simplified gitflow has only one perpetual branch master which decreases the complexity, only one ticket can be
deployed and tested in any given environment like staging or production. When only one ticket is deployed on a
given environment, it is very easy to trace a problem if it occurs. As the full gitflow, master is the stable
branch which can be deployed to production anytime.</p>

<p>If a new feature or bug fix needs to be done, the developer will follow the given steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Create a branch from latest <strong>master</strong> branch following a naming convention like feat-123 for feature no. 123</li>
<li>Work on it, after completing it push the branch feat-123 to the remote git repository (could be github or any other), preferably with just one commit</li>
<li>Open a pull request (or merge request) from the pushed branch feat-123 to <strong>master</strong></li>
<li>After the pull request is accepted, deploy it on staging environment and test it.</li>
<li>Test it, if everything is ok, create a tag from feat-123 like 12-12-14 (today&rsquo;s date) and deploy it to production</li>
<li>Test it on production, if everything is fine on production after testing merge the tag to master.</li>
</ol>


<p>The above steps are repeated for each ticket, feature of bug fix. Generally its good to wait an hour or two to merge
the tag to master to make sure at that all the things are running fine. Smaller deployments also help to increase
the overall stability of the whole systems. I am following simplified git-flow for
<a href="https://github.com/geshan/geshan.github.com/network">blogging</a> as well, for this blog source branch acts as master.</p>

<p>For a detailed example with explanation and git commands read the following slides:</p>

<center><iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/42503092" width="510" height="420" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen> </iframe></center>


<p>You can also view the <a href="http://bit.ly/1KzaNbj">interactive slides</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>I believe you have learned something new and will be willing to integrate the simplified gitflow in
your daily work with your team decreasing complexity and increasing productivity.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
